Throughout the years, I learned one
thing, that everybody can get better.
It's just where to start. Find the
starting point.
>> My name is Tim Ferriss and I'm here to
share a story with you about what can
happen when only belief meets action.
Many of us take things for granted,
things that feel second nature,
automatic, easy.
But for some people, even the simplest
tasks are challenges that must be
overcome each and every day.
Things like walking, talking, bathing,
interacting with the world in general
can feel like barriers.
It can make someone feel like they're a
prisoner in their own body.
But with a little help from the right
people, the very things that once
imprisoned us can actually become the
fire that sets us free.
And I use us because this applies to all
of us.
>> Oh, hey Tejen.
>> Yeah, hi Mr. Breckenridge.
>> Fantastic. Are you ready to conquer that
mountain?
>> Yes, I am.
>> Okay, let's do it.
>> Uh Tejen was born in Seoul, Korea two
months in premature.
So,
we stayed at the hospital for 15 days.
And around
when he was
six months, seven months, when babies
started crawling, he didn't crawl.
So, that was the first sign.
And then,
a year or a year and a half later, he
didn't try to stand up and walk.
So, we brought him to the hospital and
found out that he had
a cerebral palsy.
We did everything, every kind of
therapy, exercises for him to develop
uh to become a normal kid, but we didn't
see any improvement.
And when he started walking, he used to
walk on tiptoes.
We went to the
hospital and they recommended surgery,
but the surgery wasn't was the last
thing I want to do.
By the time he was 10 years old,
the hospital said, "If we delay surgery,
then we may not
perform the surgery anymore because of
his weight."
So, we made a painful decision to give
him surgery to put his
feet down to the ground.
And the doctor told me that uh
"You will see your son walk normal again
like a
walking." I have no choice but to give
him a surgery. So, we did it in
Heidelberg, in Germany.
So, after the surgery, his feet
were put to the ground,
but still he couldn't balance himself
well, so a small bump can trick him
and he fell down easily.
I thought that we have to do something
to
uh help him.
>> The definition of cerebral palsy has
actually changed over time. And the most
modern definition really describes this
as a clinical diagnosis that involves
onset of trouble with movement at a very
young age, typically around the time
you're born.
And this is a permanent disorder that
causes lifelong problems with mobility
and lifelong problems with movement
control.
We used to have this idea that cerebral
palsy was only related to brain injury
that somebody suffered around the time
of birth. But now, more recent data has
shown us that maybe up to 30% of
individuals with the diagnosis of
cerebral palsy actually have some sort
of genetic factor contributing to their
diagnosis. It's
absolutely essential to understand that
even if there's a genetic cause for
someone's cerebral palsy, that does not
take away the diagnosis of cerebral
palsy. And there are a variety of
causes,
um, whether it's injury or infection or
the brain develops in a different way or
a genetic cause, environmental factors.
Any of those things can result in what
we call cerebral palsy.
>> I I wanted to give him a personal
trainer, but trainers changed jobs
every once so often, so I couldn't find
a steady
uh, trainer.
And then
many years passed.
I ran into Jerzy because of, uh,
Bob, who is my one of my friends.
>> I ran a restaurant here in town, uh, my
partner and I.
And, uh,
I had managed to get myself pretty heavy
over the years.
I weighed a little over 200 lb at the
time.
It was at the point where a friend of
mine gave me a bar off of Christmas.
I saw an article in the paper about this
guy that
wrote a book Happy Body and
we went came up here to Woodside to uh
get a copy of his book and signed it for
us. Maybe 4 or 5 months later I gotten
down to uh
under 160 lbs and a friend of mine
I kept talking to him about Jersey and
what he could do. He asked me, "Do you
think it would do anything for my son?"
>> One day Bob uh asked me whether I can
see
his friend and help his son. I
said, "Of course, right?" But he said he
had he had cerebral palsy.
I said, "Well
it's not different than anybody else,
right?"
So when I uh
met
the gym first time he was uh
crouched, he hold his arms
and he was very weak, very lethargic and
walk on his toes.
He sat here
and I was looking at him, ask him
questions but
didn't get any answers really. So I
said, "It's okay, let me
get him to the gym. I thought I will put
him on a bench and let him press a bar.
I will see how strong he is on that."
He couldn't lift off. He was so weak he
couldn't lift that bar off.
And I have that bar, the bar made out of
wood, 3 lbs bar. So I put that on. I
asked him to take the bar off
and do the lift.
And he did. And I put the 5 lbs on each
side
and then it was 8 lbs. I asked him to do
it. He did it.
So I removed that, put the bar back,
that's aluminum bar. Asked him to do it.
And he did this.
But when he did
I realized that
he's going to progress here.
And he's going to progress very fast.
The father wanted
a normal
child.
I said, "Well, you have to give me 5
years
first and we'll see where we end up."
>> Jerzy is the first one who said he can
do something about my son.
There is something that can help my son.
So we signed up with
Jerzy immediately and started training.
>> And then the journey began.
Heel and toe. He Easy, easy. Slower,
slower. Heel and toe. Slower, slower.
The way I walk. Slow Slower.
Yes, this good. Right, this hard, I
know. Heel.
Toe.
Heel. Toe. Heel. Toe. Nice, okay?
Heel. Toe.
>> So if somebody has cerebral palsy,
that's just the the tip of the iceberg.
The next piece is to figure out why. And
determining why is what really helps us
to tease out now what. Let's see what
you can do. What are the base What's the
baseline level of activity? How do we
take that, strengthen it, and build on
it to really optimize functional
movement, to really optimize efficient
movement, and to really optimize your
quality of life. Now, I have to mention
that there's a wide
wide variety and wide array of severity
for CP. So, some children have very,
very minimal symptoms and other children
are profoundly affected. But, we know
that when we can really tailor
interventions to an individual and their
specific needs, that's where the magic
can happen.
>> So, from my experience, uh you know, as
a Olympic weightlifting coach, I
uh I know that
if I have 5 years of training somebody,
I can create
a major change. I called the father. I
said, "You have to come and watch it."
And uh I asked him to be present in the
gym. That's has to happen. That the
parents have to coach their children.
They cannot So, they have to We have to
shift the brains of parents that they
look at them not as people that they are
sick or ill or handicapped. They are
not.
They are just people who have the brain
that in that brain there are a lot of
boulders to move around.
>> We
went to see Jerzy twice a week
and started training.
>> Before he came, he couldn't jump up. And
he couldn't land because he was very uh
awkward and glassy. He was his his legs
were very tight and then when he uh
landed, he could fall right away. But,
after he was stepping and jumping and so
on, he started jumping on the higher
level, higher level. He was taken from
the the brain was taken from the place
to uh not able to do to actually be able
to do. So, his brain was was started
developing.
Developing pathways to the body,
controlling that body, and he started
really jumping on an 11-in box, RIGHT?
SO, I ADDED 1 LB OR 2 lb every week, and
then
uh slowly was making progressively
stronger.
Took time to accumulate
uh the the the resistance, the
the higher resistance, and then uh
adapt, so the body could adapt to that.
Because the body was getting stronger,
the body was getting more flexible, so
the body was waking up.
And the progression
of
that boy was amazing.
So, from 15 lb unable to do 15 lb to 170
lb.
So, he's a 150-lb boy that is able to
lift
press more than his body weight.
That is
more than any, you know, 20-year-old boy
can do.
That building the strength open
possibility for Tejan to be awaken.
Maybe about
maybe 6, 7 months
I
I asked father
about the changes if he sees any. I was
looking for transitions.
And he said, "He always slept." So, I
didn't hear any voice. He was in the
back of the car. But the last time
I heard a voice.
And he said, "I saw a car."
So, I asked him, "What kind of a car was
that?"
So, he didn't know. I said, "What color
was the car?" He didn't know. "It's
okay. So, you know, today when you go
home, I want you to
look at the cars outside
and remember
the car
and the color of the car, right? So, he
came back and said, "Did you see?" Said,
"Yeah, I saw two cars."
Okay. So, what is the model of the car?
Honda and Prius, right? What are the
colors? He told me the colors. I said,
"Who drove the car?"
I don't know.
And so, he came back. He told me about
the car, the color of the car, and
who drove the car. So, eventually he
memorized the car, the color, who drove
the car, how old was the person, and
driving license of that car. I was just
amazed.
The father, you know, really told me
once that his only language was
"Time to go to bed" or "Time to eat."
And it was in the situation that he said
we had the first first conversation.
>> I am grateful
for the ways
that I have changed
since I worked out
with coach Jersey.
Previously,
I did not pay attention to what was
happening around me.
I have communicated better with my
parents
by sharing my training in the gym.
In conclusion, I'm happy with the
progress that I have made.
>> Inside every person is an endless well
of potential that when unleashed can
exceed even our wildest imagination. And
sometimes all it takes is just one
person who believes in that potential.
>> So, 15 was a very interesting time for
me because it was the time of uh
um of going to high school.
My parents
didn't think like the college is for for
us, for me. It's for other people.
Not not not for me.
My father was a locksmith, so you know,
I needed to go and be a locksmith.
So, I passed the exam, went to high
school.
I was not ready for this kind of work
and study and so on.
And uh would do other things, like
drinking vodka and so on. So,
my alcoholic years began.
And I was
alcoholic until about 18. So, no school
and uh every day blackout. You know, I
had suicidal thoughts and you know, I
was
I was done almost.
And this guy
came to me.
And his mother threw his old equipment
out of the house, uh weightlifting
equipment. I said, "Well, you come to my
place
and you can uh lift in my place, right?"
And so, he brought everything and he
said, "Well,
maybe we can train a little bit." And I
said,
"No, forget about it. You train and I
will take it up."
So, uh he said, "Well, maybe we'll just
do a little bit of bench press and go
for the beer, right? For a beer." And I
look at him and say, "Beer?"
Took my attention, right?
I started doing training with him. He
was extremely weak. I mean, really weak.
The guy could barely lift a bar.
So, uh
next day,
the whole thing repeated again and again
and again and again. Then I said it's
really getting stronger and started
really feeling in my body something new,
something uh
uh
something of myself. Something uh that
the the strength was waking up in me.
It's like kind of he was
like a my angel who's pulling me out of
my alcoholism.
If you have somebody like that in life,
you're just blessed.
Now, I'm 18, 18 and a half, 19, and the
time comes to
uh
to go and to the army, because
you have to go to the army.
So, fire department offered uh
3 years of work or training,
and you could do that instead of going
to army.
And uh
that was amazing. When I first time
was in the fire engine going to the
fire,
you know, I felt something in me like a
what I've never felt before.
The feeling that
somebody needs me.
And I am that person going there. I was
so proud of myself.
It's just like
I've never had that in my life.
That
somebody really needs me, and I am that
person going there.
I was
amazing. It's waking up a bug in me.
It's high school.
I
I want to go to high school. I want to
go to college. But my friends are
already after high school,
and you know, they talk about things
that I cannot relate. I don't have
conversation
with them.
So, I go to the same high school.
And get myself into the evening classes.
There's this
soccer player, Edu, that
I I walk
about 200 m is his house. So, he comes
out of his house
and he walks with me to school
and I don't know why.
So, he walks to the high school
and then I am there and comes back
and walks with me back.
And it goes like this for a year or two.
He was really saving me.
He was
making possible for me
to go to high school and not to go and
do the
the drinking.
Oh, another angel kind of, right? That
is settling already idea in my brain
that we really need people.
If you want to go out of really a place
where it's really hard for us,
we need other people to help us,
drag us
all the way, right? And and move us
toward
help us to go to the next level.
Okay, all right. Let's do it. One.
Two.
All right, very good. Three.
Four.
Five.
Six.
Seven. You remember how was uh uh
you know, walking upstairs it was
difficult?
>> Yeah, it and I was I was all
I feel really nervous
>> Uh-huh.
>> and afraid.
>> You You used to, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Now you're okay, yeah?
>> Yeah, I'm okay now. I'm okay.
>> So,
good things are happening everywhere,
right? That that he's really not only is
uh awakened, but also he's capable talk
about that and share. He's not crashing
anymore. He uh he can now lift the leg
because I was doing a lot of training,
uh, with stepping on the higher boxes.
So, now he lifts his, uh,
foot up and down. So, he's not, uh,
shuffling, he's not tripping, he's not
really, uh, crashing down. He become
more flexible. So, one day I noticed
that his one,
uh, Tajens one, uh, shoe was shoe laces
were untied.
And the father
rush
to tie the laces. I said, "Oh, oh, oh,
stop, stop, right?" He can do that. He
was ready. He was ready to take care of
himself. And Tajen
leaned down and started really, uh,
tying his
shoes.
At that time, I asked him, "So, what
else do you do?"
Well, I said, "We do everything." I
said, "What does it mean everything?"
He said, "Well, everything. We dress
him, we
take him to the toilet, and so on,
right?" I said, "You cannot do that. The
boy is ready to take care of himself.
You have to give the boy chance."
The parents first time stop really
dressing him and
Tajen
started becoming more
independent.
You remember that Kennedy said, you
know, uh, "We don't do these things
because they are easy.
We do those things because they are
hard."
So, hard is something that
I'm always attracted to because hard it
means progress.
Easy it means repeating something. So,
it's completely useless for us.
So, this in weightlifting and any kind
of a weightlifting and coaching, hard
means finding the way
how to push the athletes to unknown, to
make that athlete uh
better over time, right?
That's the hard choice. Those hard
choices are not only are they a
spiritual hard choices, mental, and the
physical uh
everywhere, right? Hard choices, not so
simple. So, uh cerebral palsy people are
born with this condition, but that
condition doesn't get worse over time.
So, what gets worse over time is that
how they live in a society. They cannot
fit into society. They usually walk on
on toes. They uh speak slowly. They
cannot uh they are awkward. And because
of those things, they don't develop
as others do. Others look at them as as
uh
people that to comfort, to care,
but not to do anything with them, not to
really make them better. Because, you
know, medicine is doesn't do it. What
needs to be done is to coach these
people like athletes.
And when you
really engage that,
you can create progress.
They can read, they can study, they can
go to schools, and uh
you know, become like The Gen, right?
Now, he is completely independent. He is
in a place
like anybody else.
It's just he's 30 years old, and now
he's trying to figure out who he is in
this world.
He was given a second chance.
>> I am
pretty good piano player.
I practice every morning.
My dream
is to be able to study with normal kids.
>> Eventually, he passed the eighth grade
and now he's there
the college. Now he's there
time whether he would be accepted or
not.
And I talked to these people in college
and they said that they
would accept him
but
into this special program. I said, "No,
no, no, no special program. He has to be
around normal kids because he's normal.
He's capable.
He is already studying so much. He's
slow, but it's okay. He will get it. He
will get into his own time, but he needs
to be around, you know, people. He's
normal. There's nothing wrong with this
guy, right? He's okay."
>> I feel I am at
I am at the same level
just like any other
students in at college.
>> When I heard that he was accepted to
to college and I was just thinking,
"Wow.
It's just amazing thing what can be
done, right? It's what a journey this
boy went through.
What an amazing things he
he went through. And he went through it.
And he fought from within.
And he
somehow stood behind all the all the
things that he needed to do.
You know, and I felt so good. I felt
like
again like he's in this fire engine,
right?
Driving to the my first fire, I felt so
good, like
that I was
going somewhere to help someone.
>> I I I can express my thoughts
more effectively
and clearly. I have more confidence in
college at college.
>> The cerebral palsy people are not
different than any anybody else. It's
just they have
you know,
it's harder for them sometimes.
But,
they are not really different. They can
be coached, they can be trained, and
they can achieve amazing things. And who
knows what will happen to the children
with cerebral palsy?
>> So, we've been married for 40 years, and
I've watched Jersey
his
kind of genius. And
as a
as his partner in life, I always saw how
important it is for him
to see people
who are suffering and unnecessarily.
They suffer because of their ignorance,
or they suffer because uh
they are stuck in their mind, or they
imprison themselves.
He
doesn't
he cannot be an emotional.
He's emotional in the in those
situations.
>> With Teagan now off to college, Jersey
answers the call from another in search
of the dream, Jacob Zalewski, the
founder of the One Step Closer
Foundation.
>> My dad's a professional poker player, so
he kind of got me started in this whole
thing. And I went to my dad, and I was
like, "Dad, I want to start a foundation
to create a scholarship for people with
disabilities that have medical issues
that are preventing them from going
to school. We've sponsored, I believe to
this point, 12 people to with
disabilities that
able to go to college and live out their
dreams and not have their disability be
a
um
a hindrance on them.
>> Hi, you must be Jacob. You must be
Jersey.
>> Well, nice to meet you.
>> True pleasure, absolutely.
>> Are you ready for the magic?
>> Let's do it.
>> Oh,
fantastic. Let's go to the gym.
All right, let me close the door.
Okay.
>> Okay. So, how old are you? I just turned
40 in February.
>> 40?
>> Yeah.
>> Not bad considering I wasn't supposed to
be here more than 2 weeks.
>> Right. And so, you were you have been
always on
>> Yeah, I was 3 months premature.
I had the umbilical cord was wrapped
around my neck. I had a brain infection.
The doctors actually didn't think I'd
have any quality of life,
be able to eat, speak, or do anything,
and luckily they were wrong with about
95% of their predictions.
>> Uh what would be
um
the best for you, what you could really
wish for yourself to to improve?
>> Um
I guess balance,
just get better balance and and
you know, if possible, to be able to
to you know, to walk to not need the
walker as much and then to walk if if
that's a possible thing.
>> So, if I told you that you actually
could
turn to your balance and have it and
maybe walk.
>> That would be phenomenal.
>> Would you give me 3 years?
>> I'd give you 20 years.
>> All right.
>> Yeah.
>> Like that, did you? I think that 3 years
could happen a lot.
>> He helped many, many people in life and
I've watched them.
He
He would encourage them. He would
inspire them. Tell them
some good words
that they they would start moving
toward,
you know,
the right direction.
>> And so, Jersey and Jacob set out on
their own journey, a new journey, one
fueled by hope and dedication with the
belief that one day he, too, could be a
prisoner no more.
>> All this time in a body they won't hear
my mind.
I'm so much more than they believe. Draw
the line.
I won't accept this is just fine.
I'm more than who they said I'd be.
>> Oh.
More than who they
said I'd be.
Oh.
>> Cuz I'm a prisoner no more.
I'll break the chains that bind me and
I'll settle
every score.
I'm a prisoner no more.
I won't let them tell me what my
life has in store.
Cuz I'm a prisoner no more.